<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Via lactea, or, The saints onely way to true blessedness opened in a sermon from Matth. 5, 8 : also the danger of neglecting gospel-salvation, from Heb. 2, 3 / by Thomas Cheesman ... ; with his epistle to vindicate himself from those absurdities of method and language and little less then blasphemies, with which he was abused by a mercenary pen, in the former impression.</title>
            <author>Cheesman, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26784831</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26784831</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1713:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Via lactea, or, The saints onely way to true blessedness opened in a sermon from Matth. 5, 8 : also the danger of neglecting gospel-salvation, from Heb. 2, 3 / by Thomas Cheesman ... ; with his epistle to vindicate himself from those absurdities of method and language and little less then blasphemies, with which he was abused by a mercenary pen, in the former impression.</title>
                  <author>Cheesman, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the vindication of the author and satisfaction of the reader,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew V, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews II, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VIA LACTEA, or</hi> THE SAINTS Onely VVay to True Bleſſedneſs. Opened in a <hi>SERMON</hi> from MATTH. 5.8. ALSO, The Danger of neglecting <hi>Goſpel-Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> from <hi>Heb</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Cheeſman,</hi> Maſter of Arts, <hi>and formerly a Member of</hi> Pembrook-Colledge <hi>in</hi> Oxford.</p>
            <p>With his Epiſtle to Vindicate Himſelf from thoſe Abſurdities of Method and Language, and little leſs then Blaſphemies, with which he was abuſed by a Mercenary Pen, in the former Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Vindication of the Author, and Satisfaction of the Reader. 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109795:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109795:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y poor Labours in the Goſpel have been of late ſo wretchedly abuſed, and falſely repreſented to the World, as that I have been in a manner conſtrained to Print theſe following Sermons, for a neceſsary vindication of my Miniſtry, from the contempt of thoſe prophane adverſaries, who would gladly lay hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any occaſion to vilifie it, and load it with diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful imputations. In partieular, that Sermon upon <hi>Mat. 5.8.</hi> Has been moſt barbarouſly handled, and contumeliouſly dealt with, for I dare appeal to any judicious auditor, which was preſent at the delivery of it, whither the counterfeit Copy can ſhew almoſt any thing true and genuine, ſave onely the Text; that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Pamphlet, in which theſe unparalled forgeries are comprized, carries a fair and plauſible Title, flattering the Reader into expectations of ſome rich ſpiritual treaſure, but he which would take the paines to ſearch,
<pb facs="tcp:109795:3"/> ſhall find his deluded hopes entertained with nothing but droſs and dung, the very excrements of a ſottiſh diſtempered brain; in a word, the diſcourſe is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wild, brutiſh, and extravagant, as if it were ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to derive its pedigree from a pure frenſie, and were calculated for <hi>Bedlam,</hi> rather then any ſerious Chriſtian auditory, or were penned by an author who had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely renonnced all congruity of language, and had profeſſed himſelf a ſworn Enemy both to reaſon and conſcience, before he could be qualified for the work; and therefore Chriſtian Reader, for the future, I deſire thee neither to receive or give credit to any thing that ſhall come abroad in the like nature as mine But I ſhall dwell no longer upon this unpleaſing ſubject, be it known for thy further ſatisfaction, that what is here Printed, is the ſame for the main ſubſtance of it, with that which was formerly Preached, without any conſiderable addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; concerning the whole, I ſhall venture to, ſay thus much, that there is the clear water of life drawn from the wells of ſalvation, though not preſented to thee in a golden cup; wholeſome food, though the diſh be not artificially garniſhed; yet if thou be in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of hungering and thirſting ſouls, ſuch as reliſh the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, thou wilt not ſtand upon nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or delicacy. I Intreat that thou do not onely read, but weigh and conſider; never reſt ſatisfied until the truths here contained have made ſome lively impreſſion upon thy heart, ſo this and all other diſcourſes of the like nature may build thee up in thy moſt holy faith, and bring thee nearer to God, which ſhall be the Prayer of him who would gladly approve himſelf a faithful Witneſs to the truth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Cheeſman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109795:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MAT. 5.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is a deſcription of happineſs, quite contrary to the expectation of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who being ſtrangers to the ſpiritual interpretation of the Law, did commonly teach their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that they need not doubt of obtaining Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, if they did but lead civil lives; if they did but bring forth the fruits of moral honeſty, and were exactly conformable to the Tradition of their Elders. But ſays our Saviour, Do not ſatisfie your ſelves with ſuch an empty ſhadow of outward Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional, and Ceremonial holineſs; Know, it is the inward frame and diſpoſition of heart, which you are principally engaged to regard, and look after; <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, &amp;c.</hi> though there are many perſons zealous in the obſervation of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious cuſtomes, which their own fancy hath made choice of though they ſtand much upon clean Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and clean Veſſels; Though they do much
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109795:4"/> for the purifying of the fleſh, yet notwithſtanding this their outward purity, they may be objects of Gods reprobating anger, they may be condemned to periſh with the unbeleiving world, and fall ſhort of eternal happineſs; But <hi>bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> By heart here is meant all the powers and faculties of the inward man; ſo purity of heart doth imply an underſtanding free from error, a conſcience void of offence towards God and towards man, a will freed from the Dominion of ſin and Satan, affections clarified and refined from the droſs of this preſent World. <hi>Bleſſed are they that are thus pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God;</hi> that is, they ſhall enjoy him.</p>
            <p>Viſion is commonly put for fruition in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo in that place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Follow Peace and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> that is, none ſhall enjoy him; no man without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, ſhall be admitted to taſt that fulneſs of joy, or bath in thoſe Rivers of pleaſures that are at the right hand of God; or elſe we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it according to the more plain and familiar ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, <hi>and thus the pure in heart ſhall ſee God,</hi> in his work of creation, they ſhall behold him in the beautiful frame of Heaven and earth; every thing which they ſee, will put them in mind of their creatours wiſdom, goodneſs, and power; they ſhall ſee him likewiſe in the works of providence, taking notice of his hand in every mercy, and in every judgement; and they ſhall ſee him preſent in all his Ordinances; but more eſpecially they ſhall ſee him in the life to come; they ſhall ſee the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſon of Jeſus Chriſt, who is the glaſs of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109795:4"/> Trinity, and in whom thoſe who are pure in heart ſhall one day behold the fullneſs of the God-head dwelling bodily; this glaſs is of a transforming nature; for they which ſee it, ſhall be changed into the ſame likeneſs, from glory to glory. Thus much for the meaning of the words, the pure in heart ſhall ſee God, while they continue in this World, by an eye of faith; they ſhall likewiſe have a more clear immediate raviſhing and refreſhing viſion of him, when they are perfectly glorified in the life to come.</p>
            <p>The Text may be divided into a Propoſition, and a Demonſtration. The Propoſition aſſerts that the pure in heart are bleſſed; The Demonſtration or Argument which the Holy Ghoſt makes uſe of in this place, to prove their bleſſedneſs, is taken from their ſeeing of God; <hi>bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The principal Doctrine, reſulting from the words, may be this,
<q>That the pure in heart, they, and onely ſuch as they, are bleſſed; <hi>or,</hi> that true bleſſedneſs can never be obtained without purity of Heart.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the Proſecution of it, I ſhall firſt ſhew, what precious ingredients are required to make up this purity of heart. Secondly, why we ſhould labour to get purity of heart. Thirdly, what means we ſhould uſe to have our hearts purified. Fourthly, in what particulars this purity of heart will eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109795:5"/>I. There are many things implyed or comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this purity of heart. Firſt, the juſtification of our perſons; civilizing morality doth onely fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh men with ſome ſweet ſented flowers, which may perfume their outward converſation, rendring it more acceptable to humane ſociety, though ſtill their hearts may continue as filthy and impure as ever they were before. Moral men commonly have a high conceit of themſelves, and yet they may be abominable in the ſight of God, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, Prov. 30.12. <hi>There is a Generation that are pure in their own eyes, and yet is not waſhed from their filthineſs;</hi> but no true purity can be effectually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in our inward parts, until we come to be ſprinckled in the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Who hath loved us and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood.</hi> We can never be clenſed from our ſinful abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, until we be waſhed in the blood of that immaculate Lamb, which takes away the ſins of the World; when the ſoul is brought into a ſtate of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, it is cloathed in the wedding Garment of Chriſts imputed righteouſneſs, which is large enough to cover all its natural deformities, and then though it were never ſo black and filthy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it preſently appears full of amiable luſtre, and ſhining excellency, bright, and clear, beautiful as an Angel, without ſpot or blemiſh in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Purity of heart doth imply a renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our nature. We are all defiled in our very birth and conception; the poyſonous Leproſie of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſin hath ſpread it ſelf over every faculty of the ſoul, and member of the body; therefore if ever we obtain any acceptable purity, this corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109795:5"/> nature muſt be changed; hence is that Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> which you may read in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. <hi>Create in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</hi> Tit. 3.5. <hi>we are ſaid to be ſaved by the waſhing of Regeneration, and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe prays in the behalf of his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that they may be ſanctified throughout, both in body, ſoul, and ſpirit, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. The ſoul and the ſpirit are here to be diſtinguiſhed. The Spirit here ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the moſt Noble ſublime and Angelical part of man, comprehending his will, conſcience and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; the ſoul, that ſignifies the inferiour fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of ſenſitive deſires and affections, and the body that is the outward man, the inſtrument of the ſoul. In <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26. you have an excellent Goſpel promiſe, <hi>I wil ſprinkle clean water upon you, and you ſhall be waſhed from all your filthineſs, and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you; a new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you.</hi> Oh that men were generally more convinced about the excellency and neceſſity of this ſanctifying work!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, purity of heart requires the caſting out of defiling ſins; all ſin is of a very defiling nature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its ſhadowed forth in the book of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> under the notion of a ſpreading Leproſie; tis compared likewiſe to the vomit of a Dog, and to that filthy mire which Swine delight to wallow in. But more particularly, ſinful pleaſures muſt be caſt out of the heart. In the 47. of <hi>Ezek.</hi> there you read concerning the River of the Sanctuary, that is, the Doctrine of the Goſpel, which is diſperſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109795:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> amidſt the wilderneſs of the Gentiles; and moſt places where it came, received a healing vertue from it, but in the 11 <hi>verſ.</hi> the Miry places, and the Mariſhes thereof ſhall not be healed. By the Mariſhes and Miry places, ſome fitly underſtand thoſe men &amp; women that have given themſelves over to ſinful pleaſures; theſe kind of perſons are very unlikely to be healed by the waters of the Sanctuary; what groſs defilement do many contract, while they let looſe the raines to vile affections, and drown the maſculine activity of their ſpirit in a loathſome pudle of ſenſuality! Alſo earthly-mindedneſs is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin, which muſt be caſt out, if we deſire to have a pure heart. When a thing is mingled with that which is of a ſuperior nature, its thereby made more rich and precious, as when ſilver is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with gold; but if it be mingled with that which is of an inferiour nature, as ſilver mingled with lead, ſuch a heterogeneus mixture doth debaſe and impoveriſh it; thus when the ſoul of man is as I may ſo ſpeak, mingled with the graces of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, this makes it more Noble, exalting it to a higher degree of perfection. But if it be mingled with the droſſy vanities of the world, this makes it baſe and vile. The Scripture tells us concerning the pollutions of the World, 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> Cap. 2. verſ. 20. and in <hi>James</hi> 1.27. ſaith he, <hi>This is pure Religion and undefiled before God, and the father, to viſit the fatherleſs and the widows in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the world;</hi> the things of the world, they are a dirty defiling nature; they are like Pitch, tis hard to touch them and not contract ſome defilement or other. How
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109795:6"/> is it poſſible that that man ſhould have a pure heart that can be contented from morning to night, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain nothing but the world in his ſoul! <hi>John</hi> 17.15. (ſaith Chriſt,) <hi>I pray not that thou ſhouldeſt take them out of the world, but that thou ſhouldeſt keep them from the evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Purity of heart requireth that we ſhould adorn our ſelves with purifying Graces; Firſt, Hope, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. <hi>He that hath this hope, purifieth himſelf even as he is pure.</hi> Raiſed expectations of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſs, ſhould ſtir up in the ſoul ſtrong and vigorous endeavours after preſent holineſs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a defiled heart, and a undefiled inheritance, cannot ſtand together. Secondly, Faith, thats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother purifying grace; as you have it, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>Purifying their hearts by faith.</hi> Thoſe which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves, that they doe believe in Chriſt; and yet their hearts are as carnal, and corrupt, as filthy, and impure as ever they were before, They may know that their faith is but a fantaſtick dream, or deluding ſhadow; there is nothing of truth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of reality in it: Faith having tied a marriage knot between Chriſt and the ſoul, layes a ſtrong en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement upon her, to keep her ſelf chaſt and pure till the approach of her glorious Bridegroom, when ſhe ſhall be taken into the everlaſting embraces of his love. Thirdly, Repentance, that is another puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace: Repentance pulls off the mask from the face of ſin, cauſing it to appear in its proper colours; ſo that it hath no alluring paint nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit dreſs, by which it ſhould enſnare, or delude the ſoul any longer. Repentance fills the ſoul of a ſinner with hatred and deteſtation againſt ſin; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109795:7"/> him reſtleſs in his deſire, till he can procure an univerſal divorce, and perpetual ſeparation from it. Thoſe that continue impenitent, can lye ſoaking in the mire of bloody, raigning luſt, and yet not be ſenſible of the leaſt defilement; but the truly peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſoul is ſolicitous to waſh out every ſpot and ſtain. Fourthly, Love that has a notable purifying influence upon the heart; Love chiefly ſtands in a reciprocal ſimilitude of diſpoſition. They that love God, will ſtrive every day to have more and more of his likeneſs, of his picture they are ambitious to be beautified with the moſt plentiful participation of his image. They that love God, will endeavour for ſuch a meaſure of holineſs and purity as may diſpoſe and fit them to maintain a refreſhing fellowſhip and communion with God. You that can wallow in the fink of common profaneſs, without the leaſt check or remorſe of conſcience, Oh! it is a ſign you have not the leaſt dram of true love to God. Fiftly, Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of heart requireth that we ſhould be conſecrated, devoted and given up to the ſervice of God. Men of droſſy impure ſpirits look after carnal ſelf in whatſoever they doe; they aim at nothing but the pleaſing and gratifying of their fleſh; thats the great end which they propoſe to themſelves in all their actions; but thoſe who have a pure heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to glorifye God by yeilding impartial obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Commands. They act according to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel; walking in the plaineſs, candor and ingenuity of a gracious ſpirit. Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hypocrites, how ever they may cleanſe the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, yet their hearts are rotten and impure; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they onely ſerve God for by-ends and ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109795:7"/> Sixthly, purity of heart requireth that we ſhould reſiſt vain thoughts, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Oh Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, waſh thy heart from wickedneſs, that thou mayſt be ſaved;</hi> what wickedneſs was this which muſt be waſhed away, leſt it did hinder ſalvation? the holy Ghoſt tells you in the following words, <hi>how long ſhall vain thoughts lodge within thee!</hi> Thoſe which indulge themſelves in the harbouring of vain thoughts, muſt never look to have their hearts clenſed; therefore when ever thoughts begin to riſe in thy ſoul, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to ſtand and undergo a ſerious exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; if they can ſhew a paſs from the Scripture, let them go on, and be encouraged, but if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be vain, idle, and impertinent, ſend them back to hell from whence they came, not giving them the leaſt countenance or approbation.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place purity of heart requires that we ſhould bridle immoderate affections. You know, water though it be never ſo freſh and pure, while it runs in its proper Channel, yet if it overflow the banks, it will quickly grow mudy and defiled; thus thy affections if they be kept within due bounds, and proper limits, they may be pure; but when once they overflow the banks of ſobriety and moderation, they preſently are defiled. Take heed therefore leſt thy ſpirit be defiled by the irregular diſtempers and corrupt exceſs of joy, anger, carnal love, or other the like tranſporting violent paſſions.</p>
            <p>In the next place I proceed to ſhew why we ſhould labour after this purity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe without this we cannot hear the word; ſo as to profit by it; If the ſtomack be filled with corrupt matter, the moſt wholeſome food will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109795:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> prove diſtaſtful; thus when the heart abounds with impurity, the moſt ſpiritual and heavenly truths that can be delivered, will ſcarce find any acceptable or ſavoury reliſh; thoſe which cannot feed upon the word with ſuch ſweetneſs, delight, ſatisfaction, if they would ſeriouſly examine themſelves, they may poſſibly find that they have defiled their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences by ſome ſecret way of ſinning againſt God, and thats the reaſon why their hearts are ſo little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected under the Preaching of thoſe Goſpel truths, which were formerly entertained with higheſt eſteem, and were thought worthy of all accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Without this we cannot draw nigh to God in any other Religious duties. <hi>James</hi> 4.8. <hi>Draw nigh unto God, and he will draw nigh unto you;</hi> but how ſhall we be made partakers of this incomparable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge? the former words direct us, <hi>cleanſe your hands you ſinners, and purifie your hearts you double-minded.</hi> Iſaiah 1.16. <hi>waſh ye, make ye clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; come now let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord;</hi> there is no coming unto God, except we be firſt waſh'd and made clean, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13. <hi>How much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who through the eternal ſpirit offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf up without ſpot unto God, cleanſe your conſciences from dead works, that you ſerve the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God?</hi> you cannot ſerve the everliving God in an acceptable manner, unleſs your conſciences be clenſed from dead works, and this can onely be done by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who through the eternal ſpirit offered himſelf up without ſpot unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109795:8"/>3. We ſhould therefore labour for purity of heart, becauſe without this we can have no true peace; peace and purity go together. When God appears in his Majeſty and Glory, when he ariſeth terribly to ſhake the earth, and magnifies his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent power, working wonders amongſt the children of men, this is the priviledge of thoſe which are pure in heart, that they ſhall remain undaunted, becauſe conſcience will ſpeak peace to them. <hi>Job</hi> 11.14, 15. <hi>If iniquity be in thy hand, put it far away, and let not wickedneſs dwell in thy Tabernacles;</hi> for <hi>then ſhalt thou lift up thy face without ſpot; yea, thou ſhalt be ſtedfaſt, and ſhalt not fear.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.7, 8. ſaith <hi>David, purge me with Hyſop, and I ſhall be clean; waſh me and I ſhall be whiter then snow; make me to hear joy and gladneſs, that the bones which thou haſt broken may rejoyce;</hi> as if he had ſaid, Lord, I have defiled my ſelf by this bloody ſin which I have committed, and becauſe of my defilement, joy and gladneſs hath been baniſhed from my ſpirit; but do thou waſh me, purge me clean, and then the joy of thy ſalvation will be reſtored, peace will return again. Many they complain for want of comfort, for want of peace; let them conſider whither there be not ſome ſin or other that they harbour with allowance; for beleive it, one ſin will fill the heart with bitterneſs, vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and galling perplexity. Sin is a <hi>Jonah</hi> that raiſeth ſtorms and tempeſts where ever it comes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We ſhould labour for purity, becauſe without this there can be no ſcriptural wel ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hope of getting to heaven. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, Pſal.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109795:9"/> 24.3, 4. <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the Hill of the Lord? who ſhall ſtand in his holy place? hee that hath clean hands, and a pure heart, who hath not lift up his ſoul unto vanity.</hi> Thoſe that live after the fleſh, wallowing in all impurity, 'tis ſtrange, that they ſhould cheat themſelves with ſuch confident expectation of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bleſſedneſs; The new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is, <hi>Civitas Sancta, glorioſa, tota ex auro, tota gemmis et marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis decorata,</hi> (as <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſpeaks) Conſider that mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent deſcription of this City, which is laid down in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and then judge whether Goats and Swine are fit to be admitted to be its Inhabitants: A bare profeſſion may give you admiſſion into the Church Militant; but it is nothing but Scriptural ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and real purity that can give you admiſſion into the Church Triumphant; as for profane perſons, however they may flatter themſelves with vain hopes, yet while they continue in ſin, every leafe almoſt in the Bible, ſtands as a flaming ſword to keep them out of Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, We ſhould labour after purity of heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without this, there can be no perſeverance. Thoſe whoſe Religion ſtands only in a gliſtering ſhew of outward profeſſion, though they may ſeem ſtedfaſt and flouriſhing for a while, yet they will certainly fall away in an hour of temptation: What is the reaſon that ſo many have begun in the ſpirit, and ended in the fleſh; ſo many with the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> have forſaken their firſt love? It is becauſe their hearts were rotten, and corrupt from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; perhaps their heads were enriched with choice notions, curious ſpeculations, and the like; but ſtill they were ſtrangers to purity of heart, they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109795:9"/> looked upon Religion as that which could only afford matter of diſcourſe, or did conſiſt in diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for opinions.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, We ſhould labour for purity of heart, that ſo we may plentifully taſt the goodneſs of God in all conditions; that is a very remarkable place, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.1. <hi>Truely God is good to Iſrael, even to them that are of a clean heart;</hi> Whatſoever Changes, Viciſſitudes, and Revolutions, there may be in the world, yet the pure in heart ſhall experience the mercy and goodneſs of God.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, We ſhould labour to get purity of heart, becauſe the very life of Chriſtianity doth conſiſt in this. In 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.21. <hi>Baptiſme alſo now ſaveth, (not the putting away the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God.)</hi> We muſt conſider whether grace have enabled us to anſwer thoſe ſolemn engagements, which our baptiſmal Covenant laid upon us; it is inward wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing which doth principally denominate a Chriſtian. Thus much for the reaſons and motives, ſtirring up to labour after purity of heart.</p>
            <p>But in the third place, What muſt we do to get our hearts purified?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Labour to be heavenly-minded; you may obſerve, the nearer things are to heaven, the more pure they are. Water is more pure than the earth, as being higher in its ſituation; Air is more pure then water, and the Fire is more pure than the Air, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is neareſt to the heavenly bodies. If thy heart were turned and taken off from the world, if it were more raiſed to converſe with heaven, and things of an heavenly nature, this would mightily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the purity of it.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109795:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, Attend upon the word, <hi>John</hi> 15.3. <hi>Now you are clean,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>through the word that I have ſpoken unto you.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. <hi>Wherewith ſhall a young man cleanſe his way? by taking heed according to thy word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then get the ſpirit of grace to dwell in thy heart; that is the moſt effectual way to have the heart purified; the ſpirit is ſometimes compared to water for its purifying nature, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a man be born again; of water and the ſpirit, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the Kingdom of God;</hi> by water here is not meant the Element of water made uſe of in baptiſme; none can conclude baptiſmal Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſuch a place of Scripture as this; no, but except a man be born of water and the ſpirit, that is, of the ſpirit that reſembles water, compared to water for its cleanſing vertue and efficacy; ſo likewiſe the Spirit is compared to fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking concerning Chriſt, <hi>One cometh after me, greater then I, whoſe Shoe Latchets I am not worthy to unlooſe, he ſhall baptiſe you with the Holy Ghoſt, and with fire;</hi> that is, with the Holy Ghoſt, that doth reſemble fire, ſo called from its refining vertue.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place I proceed to ſhew wherein this purity of heart doth diſcover it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It diſcovers it ſelf chiefly in theſe four things, an underſtanding free from error, in purity of Works, in purity of Words, and in purity of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Firſt, An underſtanding free from error; thoſe that have a pure heart they will ſtrive againſt Errors in Doctrine, as well as Errors in Practice; for if the head be once poyſoned, the venemous influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it will quickly diſtend to the heart, infecting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109795:10"/> the very vitals of Chriſtianity; corrupt opinions, and corrupt practices commonly go together; they that have purity of heart, will be filled with a love to truth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Purity of heart diſcovers it ſelf in purity of works; if there be a conformity to the Image of God in the heart, there will alſo be a conformity to the Law of God in the outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; you may as well ſuppoſe the Sun to be without light, the fire without heat, and honey without ſweetneſs, as that ſaving grace ſhould be rooted in the heart, and not bring forth the fruits of holineſs in the life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe do miſerably cheat their own ſouls, which boaſt as if their hearts were good, though they live in the dayly practice of groſs and ſcandalous ſins; a pure fountain would never ſend forth muddy ſtreams, a good tree would never bring forth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt fruit; if filthineſs appear in the outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, you may certainly conclude that there is much more impurity in the inward parts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Purity of heart ſheweth it ſelf in puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of words, <hi>James</hi> 1.26. If any man among you ſeem to be Religious, and bridle not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this mans Religion is vain. How can the heart be chaſt, when the words are looſe and immodeſt? how can the heart be humble, when the ſpeech is ſwelling and lofty? how can the heart be heavenly, when the diſcourſe conſtantly runs out, and ſpends it ſelf upon the things of the World? the words are ſtill ſutable to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109795:11"/> that treaſure which is laid up in the heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.35. <hi>A good man out of the good treaſure of the heart, bringeth forth good things; and an evil man out of the evil treaſure, bringeth forth evil things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, They that are endued with purity of heart, labour for purity of worſhip; they are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Will-worſhip, they cannot endure to ſerve God in any way ſave that which he has appointed; they would not have the gold of the Sanctuary mingled with the droſs of humane invention; tis the coruption and uncleanneſs of mens ſpirits, which makes them ſo violently contend for, and obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to the obſervation of Idolatrous cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:109795:11"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 2.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle had told us, in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſe, <hi>that if the word which was ſpoken by the Angels,</hi> that is, the Law which was publiſhed upon <hi>Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> by the ſubordinate adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Angels: If that Word, the Law, were ſo ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt; if it obtained full authority, <hi>ſo that every tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, every diſobedience againſt it, received a juſt recompence of reward;</hi> If men were ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for tranſgreſſing the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> how much more ſhall we be ſeverely puniſhed, if we ſin againſt the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt! <hi>How ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would willingly ſpend the ſhort time allotted for the preſent exerciſe, in that diſcourſe which might moſt conduce to general edification: And therefore I ſhall without further delay preſent to you this doctrinal point of Obſervation, from the words to be inſiſted upon, Namely,
<q>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109795:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> That thoſe which go on in the final neglect of that Salvation which is offered and held forth in the Goſpel, they muſt unavoidably periſh.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the Handling of the point I ſhall propoſe this enſuing method.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew what this ſalvation is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Why it is called a great Salvation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How many wayes men are guilty of neglecting this great Salvation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, What are the cauſes from whence the general neglect of this <hi>great Salvation</hi> may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I ſhall wind up all in ſome uſefull appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What this <hi>Salvation</hi> is.</p>
            <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, properly ſignifies the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of any thing or Perſon in a ſtate of ſafety. But in the Scripture it is taken divers ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is taken for a Deliverance from ſome temporal danger or calaminity. Thus you have it in <hi>Exodus</hi> 14.13. When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with an Army of <hi>Egyptians</hi> at their backs, and the Red Sea was before them, and that the murmuring of the people might be ſatisfied, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtands up, and bids them <hi>ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord;</hi> as if he had ſaid, Let not your hearts be troubled, let not your ſpirits ſink under a load of diſcouraging fears, do not fall into the hands of unbeliefe; for that is worſe than if you ſhould fall into the hands of your enemies; but have a ſtedfaſt eye unto the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo take
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109795:12"/> notice what a ſeaſonable and ſpeedy deliverance he will work for you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Salvation is taken for the providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al care and power of God, whereby he will not let his people want thoſe things that are needfull. Thus you have it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.22. When the Iſraelites murmured againſt God in the Wilderneſs for want of food, why ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>They truſted not in his ſalvation, they believed not in God, and truſted not in his ſalvation;</hi> that is, They truſted not in that wonderful providence of God which would certainly make a proviſion for them in their wants and difficulties, had they but patience to wait for it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Salvation is taken in ſcripture for the Author of ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1. <hi>The Lord is my light and my ſalvation; whom ſhall I fear?</hi> ſo in <hi>Luke</hi> 2.30. they are the words of <hi>Simeon, Now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace,</hi> verſe 30. <hi>for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation,</hi> that is, I have beheld him that ſhall be the Author of ſalvation both to the Jews and to the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Salvation is taken for that ſtate of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and perfect Bleſſedneſs which the ſoules of Gods people ſhall enter upon immediately after the diſſolution of their bodies.</p>
            <p>Thus you have it in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. ſpeaking there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c rning the Angels, <hi>Are they not all miniſtring ſpirits ſent forth that they may miniſter for thoſe which ſhall be the heirs of ſalvation?</hi> the <hi>heirs of ſalvation,</hi> that is, the heirs of future Glory.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, Salvation is ſometimes Metonymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally taken for the doctrine of the Goſpel, becauſe that is the only way which God hath ordinarily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109795:13"/> for the ſalvation of his rational creatures.</p>
            <p>And thus it is taken in the words of the Text, <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have finiſhed the firſt Branch, and proceed to the ſecond, to enquire why this is here called a <hi>great Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, It is ſo called becauſe it doth concern our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Oh! that men were more deeply ſenſible of the incomparable excellency and preciouſneſs that is in their ſoules! Why, Pleaſure is a Dream, Honour is a ſmoak, Wealth is a deceitful ſhadow; Our ſoules are the onely jewels, that are worth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving. If theſe be ſaved, no matter what is loſt; and if theſe be loſt, no matter what is ſaved.</p>
            <p>Alas! What would all the preferments the world can give, avail us if after the enjoyment of all, our ſouls ſhould be ſwallowed up in a gulf of remedileſs torment? I tell you, and there is ground for it in the word of God, that the loathſome toad and the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſnake, they are in a better condition than the higheſt unſanctified Monarch upon the earth who ſhall be condemned to have his portion in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life. If you highly eſteem thoſe things or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which may be inſtrumental for the ſaving of your eſtates, or to ſave the life of your bodies; are you not infinitely much more engaged to ſet an high eſteem upon the Goſpel which God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the only inſtrument for the ſaving of your ſouls? Why, our time is here ſpent to very little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, unleſſe we do induſtriouſly promote the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our ſouls. We live here in vain unleſs that ſhort time which is allotted for us to continue here
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109795:13"/> upon the earth, be wiſely improved to prepare us for an everlaſting enjoyment of God in heaven; it had been better for us that our bodies had never lived the life of nature, unleſs a life of grace here, diſpoſe our ſoules for a life of Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thoſe which lay out all their care to cheriſh frail periſhing bodies, and in the mean time neglect their ſoules, they goe the ready way to plunge both body and ſoul in everlaſting ruine. For oh ſinner, doſt thou not know, that at the Reſurrection thy body ſhall be in the ſame condition with thy ſoul? when they are reunited together, they muſt be both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in joy, or companions in torment.</p>
            <p>But, when the care which we lay out upon our bodies, is nothing, if compared with the care which we lay out upon our ſoules, we go the ready way to ſave both, to make both eternally happy; that is the firſt reaſon, it is called a great ſalvation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it concerns our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That ſalvation which the Goſpel brings, is therefore called a great ſalvation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is often beſtowed upon the greateſt Sinners.</p>
            <p>There is no perſon ſo deeply defiled with the pollutions of the world, or grown ſo black with the guilt of high and hainous ſins, but that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel can furniſh him with a robe of imputed Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs large enough to cover all his ſpots, and ſtains, to conceal all his ſhame and nakedneſs in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God.</p>
            <p>No perſon hath ſo much run upon the ſcore of divine juſtice, but the Goſpel can bring him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with a Surety which is able to diſcharge his debt, and pay the utmoſt farthing. Never yet
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109795:14"/> did any ſinner come to Chriſt, and Chriſt refuſed to ſave him, meerly upon this account becauſe his ſins were too great to be pardoned; there never was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had occaſion for ſuch a complaint; No, the greateſt ſinner in this congregation may be encouraged; Thoſe which for many years together have continued ſlaves to the Prince of darkneſs, thoſe which have ſpent the flower of their age, in the ſervice of ſin, and making proviſion for their luſts, thoſe that have trifled away their time, that have abuſed the patience of God, that have trampled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot the riches of his goodneſs, that have reſiſted the work of grace, and grieved the Spirit, why yet if they will accept Chriſt, and come up to the terms of the Goſpel, they ſhall not miſs of a full ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This is called a very great ſalvation in regard of the great price which was laid down to procure it. God ſcornes to ſell ſalvation to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; it is therefore freely offered unto us; we may have it without money, and without price; Oh! but it coſt Chriſt full dear; it coſt him no leſs than the ſhedding of his own <hi>precious Blood,</hi> the leaſt drop of which was more worth than the whole frame of this material world; if all the mountains had been turned into gold, and every blade of graſs on the face of the earth, had been changed into a precious Jewel, and all this laid together had been offered up to procure the ſalvation of but one ſingle perſon, yet it would not have been accepted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This is a very <hi>great ſalvation</hi> if we conſider thoſe great benefits that are comprehended in it; why, this ſalvation, it doth comprehend <hi>Adoption, Juſtification,</hi> and <hi>Eternall life.</hi> The benefits are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109795:14"/> great; though men are naturally born veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of wrath, and fire-bands of hell; why yet the Goſpel ſhews them how they may get into a ſtate of <hi>peace and reconciliation with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Goſpel ſhews them how they may have their ſins forgotten and forgiven; how they may have their perſons juſtified, and their natures ſanctified, that they may be made meet to be partakers of an inheritance with the ſaints in light.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, This is called a <hi>great ſalvation</hi> becauſe it brings a great revenue of Glory to the excellent Name of God: God is more glorified in that ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is extended to ſinners in the Goſpel, than by any thing elſe; why, here in this Salvation the riches of his wiſdome are diſcovered, his juſtice is ſatisfied, his grace and love are exalted, his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſparkles forth to the greateſt advantage.</p>
            <p>And then in the ſixth place, It is a <hi>great ſalvation</hi> if we conſider its everlaſting nature. Thoſe that are once effectually called, and juſtified, though they may fall under the merit of condemnation, yet they ſhall never be brought into a ſtate of condemnation; they that are once the children of God, ſhall ſo remain for ever; <hi>for the gifts of God are unchangable;</hi> they ſhall ſure enough <hi>be kept by the mighty power of God through faith unto ſalvation.</hi> They that are once made partakers of this <hi>Salvation,</hi> though they may be encompaſſed with trouble, why yet their graces are ſafe, their comforts are ſafe; Chriſt, their head, their hope, and all is ſafe. This is the ſalvation concerning our ſoules, being beſtowed upon the greateſt ſinners, having a great price laid down to purchaſe it, comprehending great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits,<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109795:15"/> bringing great glory to the name of God, and being of an everlaſting nature, juſtly called a very great Salvation.</p>
            <p>I haue finiſhed the ſecond thing propoſed, and come to the third, inquiring how many ways per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be guilty of neglecting this great Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And firſt, men are guily of neglecting this great Salvation when they will not obey the Goſpel; whoſoever lives in the practice of any known ſin, in a ſtate of open rebellion againſt God, preſuming to out-face the Sun of Goſpel light, (Oh that God would powerfully ſpeak to his heart, and effectually convince him of it!) this perſon is guilty of neglecting this great Salvation. Why ſirs, why doth the great God of Heaven ſpeak to poor wormes here upon the earth, unleſs it be that they ſhould obey him? and how can perſons more evidently diſcover that they deſpiſe the Goſpel of Chriſt, then when they will not give up themſelves to be ruled and governed by it? when they will not ſuffer it to have any transforming or reforming efficacy upon their hearts, &amp; when they peremptorily refuſe to live up to the purity of a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel converſation; but though the word be never ſo much Preached, yet they ſtill wallow in their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines; the Swearer, the Sabbath-breaker, the Perfidious perſon, the Scorner at an holy life, will ſtill be the ſame, ſay the Preacher what he will. If Goſpel Miniſters call upon the Drunkard to be ſober, and watch leaſt he be drowned in the next intemperate cup of Wine, and he be ſnatcht away by death in the midſt of his ſin, as many others have been in the like condition, before him: why
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109795:15"/> yet he will not be prevailed upon, to break off his revelling courſes. Though Miniſters would fain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the covetous wretch to ſeek after the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and to lay up treaſure in Heaven, and to look after an inheritance of a better nature then the World can give, why yet he ſtill remaines a ſlave to unrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> he ſtill continues rooting like a Swine in the earth. Though they call upon the laſcivious perſon to put on the Ornaments of chaſtity, and to poſſeſs his veſſel in ſanctification and honour; why yet when they have ſpoken all that can be ſpoken, the Whore muſt ſtill be followed, and Chriſt be rejected. Alas! Friends, meer nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Chriſtians, by their wicked converſation they are a perpetual reproach to the name of Chriſt. <hi>Cyprian</hi> brings the Heathens in his days, thus up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding the Chriſtians, <hi>Quare in ore ſemper evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, evangelium, cum tua vita ab evangelii praeceptis diſcrepat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is the Goſpel ſo much in their lips, when there is nothing of Goſpel purity that appears in their lives? Why? you may be ſure that Miniſters were not ſent that they ſhould be as muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to gratifie the ears of the people with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſounds, nor to feed the wanton curioſity of nice critical hearers with choyce refined notions; Chriſt did not ſend his Goſpel that it ſhould onely furniſh men with matter of diſcourſe and empty ſpeculations; No, but the holy Apoſtle tells you why the Goſpel was ſent, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>The grace of God that brings ſalvation, hath appeared to all men;</hi> to what end? why, <hi>Teaching us, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109795:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world, looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie to himſelf a peculiar people, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of goodworks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, men are guilty of neglecting this great ſalvation, when they will not lay to heart the things of the Goſpel; when they count it a burthen to be engaged in meditating upon them, when they will not conſider nor allow the Goſpel any room in their ſerious thoughts, but rather do what they can to baniſh and caſt it out of their minds; how can you more evidently diſcover that you deſpiſe a thing, then when you do not judge it worth the thinking upon?</p>
            <p>Oh! how many are there, that melt themſelves into luxury, and wantonneſs, rufling it out into pride and bravery, and waſting their precious time? yet they never took any ſucceſsful care for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial ſouls; they never ſet apart one hour ſeriouſly to conſider how they might provide for their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtate.</p>
            <p>Alas! what will become of thoſe men? do they not think that they ſhall taſte of Death as well as others? and then how can they look their Judge in the face? I beſeech you ſinners, take notice of the indiſpenſible neceſſity that lies upon you to practice the duty of conſideration. Is Chriſt before you, is grace and a crown of glory before you, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109795:16"/> will you not conſider? why is Death ready to ſeize upon you, is the judge at the door, and yet will ye not conſider? why, have you any better things to conſider upon then the Goſpel doth afford? what is not a God and a Chriſt, is not the ſtate of your ſouls worth the conſidering upon? why, Crowns, and Kingdoms, Lands, and Lordſhips, they are but toys and trifles, but chaff and ſtubble, droſs and dung, if compared with thoſe everlaſting things; and yet will you not be perſwaded to conſider? Alas! doth not Conſcience tell you that you can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain wanton, and covetous, and revengeful thoughts from morning until night, and that is no weariſomeneſs to your ſpirits; and have you no lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, no time to think how you may make your peace with God, and procure the pardon of your ſins? That is the ſecond; Men are guilty of neglecting this great Salvation, when they will not meditate upon the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Men are guilty of neglecting this great Salvation, when they will not put forth their ſtrength to work out their own Salvation; when they reſolve to be at no further coſt for the ſaving of their ſouls, then the laying out of a few cold cuſtomary deſires, and ſluggiſh wiſhes; why con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what work you have to do, if ever you will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into life; you have a dark underſtanding to be enlightned, an hard heart to be ſoftned, a ſtubborn will to be ſubdued, defiled affections that muſt be cleanſed, ſtrong corruptions that muſt be mortified, violent temptations that muſt be reſiſted, and can
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109795:17"/> all this be done, while you ſleep in the boſome of brutiſh ſecurity, and ſlothful negligence? why, doth not the Scripture tell you that if you will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>you muſt ſtrive to enter in at the straight gate? for many ſhall ſeek to enter and ſhall not be able;</hi> you muſt <hi>wreſtle with Principalities and Powers, ſo run that you may obtain, and fight the good fight of faith, that you may lay hold upon eternal life;</hi> and do ſuch expreſſions as theſe, give the leaſt encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to ſloath. Oh! that men ſhould take more paines to get a morſel of bread, then they do to get an immortal Kingdom of glory! that they ſhould go to bed late, <hi>and riſe early, and eat the bread of carefulneſs,</hi> as if they never could take too much pains for the getting of earthly riches! yet think every hour too much that is ſpent for the things of eternity; thoſe which will not put forth their ſtrength in working out Salvation, they are guilty of neglecting it.</p>
            <p>But in the fourth place, what are the cauſes from whence the general neglect of this ſalvation may proceed.</p>
            <p>Why, firſt ignorance, many are ſo ignorant, as that they do not underſtand the common termes of Chriſtianity; though Miniſters do cloath their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the plaineſt and moſt familiar expreſſions, yet they hear all as if the diſcourſe were delivered in an unknown language.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109795:17"/>
            <p>Secondly, another cauſe is unbelief, <hi>why men neglect this great Salvation;</hi> though they have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent meaſure of knowledge, yet they do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Goſpel of Chriſt to be true, they dont hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily believe that tis the word of God, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with their tongues they may profeſs to believe as well as others, leaſt they ſhould be ſhamed by the company with whom they converſe yet in their hearts they have no ſtedfaſt perſwaſion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth of theſe things; if there were not ſo much unbeleif, men would be a great deal more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in working out their Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Multorum fides natat in labris, dum nulla eſt in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, aut vehementer languet;</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Cyprian</hi>) many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to have faith, when nothing but the works of infidelity appear in their lives.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Hardneſs of heart, that is another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; men are hard enough by nature; but by cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary continuance in ſin, and by grieving the ſpirit, and by ſlighting the means of grace, they grow har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; ſo that their hearts will not be broken under the threatnings of the Law, nor melted under the promiſes of the Goſpel; A broken heart can no more neglect the Goſpel, than an hungry man can neglect his food.</p>
            <p>But Fourthly, The greateſt cauſe of all in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men, is earthly-mindedneſs; they are ſo taken up with the things of the world, that they have no leiſure to think of heaven; their thoughts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109795:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> are earthly, their project and endeavours are earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their affections earthly; head, heart, hand, and all conſpire to carry on thoſe deſigns, on which their temporal advantages do eſpecially depend. You know in <hi>Mathew</hi> 13.22. thoſe hearers that are compared to the thorny ground, <hi>they received the word, but the cares of the world, and the deceitfulneſs of riches, choaked the word, ſo that it became unfruitful;</hi> they were never the better for it. If a perſon goes aſide to conſider about the matters of his ſalvation, preſently ſome worldly buſineſs or other ſteps in and interrupteth his thoughts. The young man in <hi>Matthew</hi> 19. was very fair for heaven; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the world that was a bar to him; for ſaith the text, <hi>he went away ſorrowful, becauſe he had great poſſeſſions;</hi> Chriſt and the world, they are contrary Maſters, and they ſet their ſervants about a contrary work; therefore none can ſerve both of theſe together.</p>
            <p>I come to the firſt and laſt thing, which is to wind up all in ſome uſefull application.</p>
            <p>And firſt, If thoſe which neglect the ſalvation of the Goſpel, muſt unavoidably periſh: then let all take heed how they do attend and give ear to the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>For firſt, there is much of God and Chriſt in the Goſpel, there are thouſands, amongſt the glorified ſaints and Angels, bleſſing the Name of God for ever for that which they met withal in the preaching of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109795:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> the word; if it were poſſible that ſin ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in heaven, that would be greater than ſin here committed upon the earth; therefore the ſin of the fallen Angels was the greater, becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in a place, where God was pleaſed to make ſpeciall and extraordinary diſcoveries of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; the more of God there is in any thing, the greater is their ſin who abuſe it; there is more of God in the Goſpel, then there is in all the works of the Creation and providence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We ſhould have a care, leaſt we be found guilty of neglecting the Goſpel, becauſe that is the conduit, which God hath appointed to convey the choiceſt bleſſings to the hearts of his people; Thoſe that live under the faithful and powerful diſpenſations of the Goſpel, let them know that they enjoy the greateſt priviledge, which they are capable of receiving in this life. Oh then what ſhall we think of thoſe poor ſoules, which have continued for many years, and are grown gray-headed under the preaching of the Goſpel, and yet are never the better for it! every Sermon hath been like a ſhower of water, falling upon a rock, making no impreſſion at all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Therefore do not neglect the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, becauſe it is very quick and lively in its work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it will quickly bring men into a ſtate of Salvation, or elſe ſinke them deeper into perdition, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>the word of God is quick and powerful</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and ſharper
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109795:19"/> than a two-edged ſword, and pierceth even to the dividing aſunder of the ſoul and ſpirit:</hi> Math. 3.10. <hi>Now the Ax</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is laid unto the root of the Tree, and every Tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewen down and caſt into the fire; The Ax is laid to the root of the Tree;</hi> When was that? Why, when <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> came preaching repentance, <hi>becauſe the kingdome of God was at hand;</hi> the preaching of the Goſpel was at hand; though the tree was barren before, yet it might ſtand ſtill, and not be cut down; but now when the powerful miniſtration of the word cometh, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cloſe with the Goſpel and be ſaved, or elſe refuſe the Goſpel and periſh, So <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15, 16. <hi>Goe</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and preach the Goſpel to every creature. He that beleeveth, and is baptized ſhall be ſaved; and he that beleeveth not ſhal be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, therefore we ſhould not neglect the Goſpel, becauſe it is that by which we muſt be judged at the laſt day. Heathens that never heard of Chriſt, they ſhall not be puniſhed for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving in him; for obligation unto duty doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily preſuppoſe the promulgation of a Law; but as for thoſe that have lived under the Goſpel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſie they ſhall be judged according to the Goſpel; what would many a perſon give to know how it ſhall ſpeed with him in that great and notable day, <hi>when the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a mighty noiſe, and the Elements melt with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109795:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> heat,</hi> when all the beauty and bravery of the World, ſhall ſink into a bed of aſhes? what would many a man give to know how he ſhall ſpeed then? why, the Goſpel tells you; thoſe which the Goſpel doth condemn now, they ſhall be condemned then; and they that are acquitted by the Goſpel now, they ſhall be acquitted then.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, All that neglect the Goſpel, they are near to a curſe, &amp;c. There is a clear place for it in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.7, 8. <hi>The Earth which drinketh in the rain, that cometh oft upon it, and bringeth for Herbs, meet for them by whom it is dreſſed, receiveth a bleſſing from God, but that which bringeth forth briars and thornes, is rejected, and is nigh unto curſing, whoſe end is to be burned;</hi> the meaning of it is briefly thus, the good ſoyl are thoſe honeſt hearers which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the word, and bring forth fruit, and receive a bleſſing from God; but that which bears briars and thornes, the bad ground, is thoſe hearers which receive the word, hear as many Sermons as others, yet they bring nothing forth but briars and thornes, repining and murmuring againſt the purity and truth of Goſpel-Ordinances; <hi>theſe are rejected, and are nigh unto curſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then in the laſt place thoſe that do neglect the Goſpel, it will deeply agravate their condemnation. The <hi>Sodomites</hi> that were conſumed with fire and brimſtone from Heaven, you will ſay they were great ſinners, and yet Chriſt tells us plainly, it will be more tollerable for them at the day of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109795:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> judgement, then for thoſe that neglect the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if it be ſo dreadfull to neglect the Goſpel; then endeavour to receive the Preaching of the Goſpel, as Chriſt hath appointed; receive with meekneſs that ingrafted word which is able to ſave your ſouls. I ſhall onely name theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Receive it with reverence and attention, as thoſe which muſt give an account to the Lord of Glory for every Sermon which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Receive it with thankfulneſs; we give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for the ſhining of the Sun, and for the dropping of the clouds, and for fruitful ſeaſons; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeldome do we break forth into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, for the unſpeakable benefit of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Receive it with an holy hunger, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after it; as new born Babes deſire the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Milk of the word, that you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereby.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
